good morning everybody
i want to lead off with a quote from
a great man of the novice prince
he divides the world
everything is about power everything has
to have a side everyone knows what side
they should pick
pick it and you're a collaborator
rejected a dissident
are you not are you or are you not on
the side of power
if your actions were completely selfish
if you were an utterly egocentric
sociopath
if your only goal was to get ahead and
make a good impression
what would you pretend to believe what
words
what ideas would drip from your mouth
and to whose newsletter would you
subscribe
this side is the side of power
to take power aside is to collaborate
stand against it
is to descend and this doesn't tell us
who's right or wrong
real life is not a movie if there was
some cheap and accurate formula for
right and wrong
how would any wrong remain
this document goes on to propose a third
option
not collaborating with power but not
dissenting against power
because what both of those sides are
doing
is acknowledging power
acknowledging power right but the power
only has power because we all
acknowledge it
if we stopped it would go away
um i had a conversation last night with
a with a homeless woman
and about 10 minutes into the
conversation i realized that this is one
of the only
people i've spoken to in a long time who
isn't lying to me
she has nothing to gain
she was just talking about how she felt
honestly
i think one of the scariest things that
we're going to have to come to grip with
grips with in the next 20 years
is that you are an algorithm
it doesn't make it okay for others
to treat you like that though
i don't have a universal solution
the only thing i know for now is
don't be a dissident don't be a
collaborator
detach
so who did their homework
who read the paper
so
i didn't read all of it um but i read
enough to i think
begin uh tackling the problem
so if you recall from yesterday's stream
the problem that we're trying to
solve is busy people five
um busy beaver five is saying
uh what is the longest
running or most one's printing
a five-state two-value turing machine
naively there's 63 trillion of these
machines
what we're first focusing on is reducing
the total number of machines
down to something much more approachable
by using the fact
that a lot of machines are um
so there's a few ways there's a few
classes that we can remove so we can put
machines in equivalence classes
uh saying that this machine is
equivalent to these other hundred and
therefore we only need to check one of
them
if you want to check one of the other 99
just refer to this one it's guaranteed
to have the same outcome
we can also potentially remove machines
that cannot possibly be the winner
for busy beaver i think maybe the way to
think about this
is uh domination so what they talk about
in the paper is this idea of one halting
so one halting is a machine that well
they define k halting to be how many
halting states a machine has
so if we look
go at to
it's not on this page
this is the just the busy beaver
programming in general see non-regular
page yeah so these are these are turing
machines
and if you'll notice they all have one
halting state
in fact this is kind of cute they've
even defined the uh the halting state to
always be b0
uh so the only there are two states that
are special
and that's discussed in this paper the
two special states are the halting state
and state a and state a is special
because the machine begins execution
state
a uh machine states are labeled a b c
d e where a is the initial state of the
machine the halting state is labeled z
here they use h
so you'll notice that uh
yeah when searching for busy beaver
machines it seems natural to focus on
machines which are one halting
exhaustive and maximizing
um so
the maximizing machine seems to just
mean that the last step
the the step to halt it always writes a
one
if you're trying to maximize the number
of ones uh it makes sense to make it one
if you're trying to maximize the runtime
it doesn't matter at all
so we can only focus on the maximizing
machines and say that this number has to
be one
the paper makes a note that uh
k halting machines where k is greater
than one
because we're only focused on one
execution
of the tiring machine we're only focused
on the execution of that turing machine
on a blank tape
only one halting transition can be used
so whichever halting transition is used
the unused one can be replaced with
anything and it will clearly never get
executed
so then they go on to define activity
and productivity
so activity is the number of steps the
machine runs
productivity is the number of ones that
it writes to the tape
now they talk about how yeah if the
activity of m
is infinity meaning the machine does not
halt then the productivity of amazon
defined
i thought about that for a little bit
and at first i thought okay well you
know it probably writes an infinite
number of ones to the tape but this
obviously isn't true you could imagine a
turing machine that
marches a one onward to infinity
and this machine is actually defined to
have a productivity of one oh well
sure enough i mean it depends yeah how
do you define the productivity for an
infinite machine
i guess it actually cannot have a state
where the one moves because there's no
way to do an atomic swap
you can do an average of one
um but i think yeah i think you could
talk about limits of machines but
not really relevant to what we are
discussing here so they define a class
of things that can make it irrelevant to
the visibility problem
um if the machine does not halt
if the machine is actually has less
activity than the total number of states
uh if the productivity is zero meaning
one way to know that the productivity is
going to be zero in fact even for an
infinite
even for a non-halting turing machine i
guess you can still say the productivity
is zero
if all if it can't write ones to the
tape imagine all of those numbers are
zero
um now figuring out whether activity is
finite is of course the halting problem
so we're not going to have a decision
procedure for that
but the halting problem it's frequently
misunderstood to be
to say that you can never know whether a
program halts or not
and this is obviously ludicrous um
there's many programs that
you can show they halt just by running
them and then oh it halts
there's also many programs that you can
write trivially small proofs
um that they do halt now
what i was thinking about and this this
starts to approach the limits of my
mathematical knowledge is
how do you show that a machine doesn't
halt
so there's one way to show it which is
to have it repeat a state
if you can show it to repeat the state
it doesn't halt otherwise
is it always some form of induction
right you could imagine
that the marching one turing machine
using induction to show that it doesn't
halt
and this is about where i got to in the
paper so we're going to read
uh the rest together
sorry i did what i what i spent time on
last night
instead of reading the paper and that
i'm very sorry people i made hammer
uh
hammer like backspace is another one of
these maybe companies
our mission is to organize the world's
information and make it accessible to
anyone who pays hammer
thirty dollars a month our motto is and
this is all in quotes don't be evil and
if we ever remove this motto it's
because we are evil now
and our slogan is better searched better
results
hammer you can check it out at hammer
dot
law uh and i think one
i'm thinking about that
i have a theory that companies that have
law domains
are less likely to become evil
you find not all self-serious people are
evil but i think
are all evil people self serious
i think they might be yes papa john's
right
don't sue me bro don't sue me don't
shoot me as
parody man it's parody yo
uh yeah a hammer it's a hammer just
gonna smash
google
yeah but
nothing can compute busy b for numbers
uh busy beaver numbers
are uncomputable
at least all of them
um so this is a template for many
machines as the machine will only be
executed on blank inputs
all transitions
gutless go on
i still don't totally understand their
definition like why are there
two
oh i guess so this is in state one
if there's a zero present we write a one
and we move to the right in state two
right
so that will just march like that and
then
i don't think it matters what you fill
in there
um
yeah okay so i think we can say for each
one of these
graphs we would expect an exiting node
with both a z or for each one of these
uh graph uh vertices we would expect an
edge with a zero and a one
so i think that is true
input output direction new state
so this is the the quintuple
form of the turing machine
the most important consequence of
requiring the blank tape condition
is that it will reduce the number of
machines that are considered so
there's
a couple ways to talk about this
problem and maybe i don't want something
as strict as what they're doing
i would be okay with say 5x more
machines
to not start excluding machines that are
only
this exclusion stage does not have to be
aware of the
problem this is a problem aware
exclusion
uh which it would be nice if we could
kind of break it up into two steps a
non-problem aware exclusion and then a
problem aware exclusion
so if we can show the two machines
behave completely identically for
example with relabeling the states or
switching left and right
then it's much it's more universal and
we can always do the second step later
um so requiring the blank tape condition
is
something that is specific to the busy
beaver problem
um aren't there useful graph theory
techniques to reduce the space of
possible machines yeah
in a way you can talk about this as a
graph isomorphism
uh problem
so the techniques that were historically
used before this paper are
techniques that uh run the machines
while they're finding them which i don't
really like
um this is something we talked about in
the last stream
um
this stuff seems kind of interesting
for an end state m symbol quadruple
machine
is an equivalent quintuple machine
we're only interested in evaluating
machines only blank input
which means to reduce the number of
machines that require non-trivial
analysis
so this is again doing i said i would
implement what this paper does
that's what i said i would do on today's
stream so i think we should try to do it
uh i mean one we can also read they gave
a nice bit of prologue code
this is the harland paper and they gave
a nice bit of prologue code here
when i tried to run the prolog code it
didn't work
this thing called emulate search let's
see what emulate search does
now let me go back to you guys
very typical of academic code to just
have all this stuff commented out and
not use a logging system
who knows if prologue actually has a
logging system
okay
when generating machines for the busy
vehicle problem
it seems intuitively natural to
concentrate on machines that are one
halting exhaustive and maximizing
we can ensure the machine is maximizing
by specifying that any halting
transition must be of this
this form so they use r but they're
equivalent to the l machines
it is more difficult to say that a
machine is exhaustive and
one halting
wait what isn't one halting really
easy oh i guess if it's a disconnected
graph it's not one halting obviously you
can have one halt transition
but that whole transition may not be
connected to the a state
that's what they're about to say right
if you imagine a halt you can imagine a
machine that's just like
jumps between the a and b states
repeatedly and then has a different
graph over there and that's where the
halting state is
you like the approach of lazily
extending the machine
yeah the the downside in this paper
that's discussed is is pretty uh
reasonable
it says that you know they're grouping
still two steps together here the more
we can
look at this like a a search problem
where we're
uh removing things at each step it
allows us to debug
evaluate and contemplate each problem in
isolation
not as a big group it'll also reduce
runtime
okay
consider the following partial
machine oh man this also skull is going
to run into rice's theorist
crisis theorem racist time the racist
theorem is
let's let's go to our own private copy
of wikipedia and look up isis damn
so nice to be on your own private
internet
where you know notice how i haven't
gotten a single pop-up
a single bit of spam this is my own
private internet
that's what we're gonna do at the
college
the college we're gonna have a really
nice private internet
uh millisecond latency right you're
talking like millisecond ping times
um we'll have copies of wikipedia
uh we'll have local running things like
like uh like a local
uh get lab instance which we can run
at the scale of a college
and hopefully i mean it's not like
you're only going to have access to this
right we're not putting a great firewall
up
but hopefully one of our metrics of
success
will be if students are using
the local internet more and more as the
real internet degrades in quality
our local internet can uh
can can be a
holdout we can do this because
obviously students can contribute to the
local internet
but with strong community
there won't be crap on it
brick and mortar university boys that's
the way to do it
that's the way to do it you gotta do it
that way you know there's always online
learning stuff
do you want to go to harvard and pay the
same amount of money
for a bunch of coursera courses but you
get a harvard
degree
um yeah no our private internet intranet
is going to be great
uh i'm not i'm not wading into the
crap blogosphere thank you by the way
uh for putting
the content the content is now uh
unsliced our codex is back available
thank you scott alexander for doing that
um it turns out only crackpots are
interested in cults
which i guess if i'd thought about it a
little bit is not surprising
but that's why there will not be a cult
just a university
um yeah so righteous theorem this is
what we're talking about
so let's let's let's read this text
carefully
consider the partial machine in figure 9
which is generated as part of the
process
let's figure 9 here we go of generating
five state two symbol machines
execution of this partial machine
they're still using execution it seems
brings us to the configuration 1d10
one oh 1d10 so that's
they talked about this notation earlier
in the paper so this
is means the turing machine head is
actually on top of this one
and it's in state d
so what should our choices be for the
transition the set of states used in the
machine so far is abcd
and the set of symbols so far used as
zero and one this means we have all the
symbols necessary for a two symbol
machine
but have only used four states
here we should consider only the
possibilities zero one
lr oh
so note that it can't halt yet because
if it were to halt on that transition it
would never get to state e and then the
machine would not be
maximal um
man this is using the same kind of
same kind of like run the machine
approach as tree normal form
um
all right let's
we could ask the question what is the
reduction factor of tree normal form on
three and four
and maybe the reduction factor would be
similar for five
uh
our next decision for the transition
okay so it made that
that d transition uh because it was over
a one so it made the transition to the
zero state and now it's in
yeah this gives us a machine in ten in
in this configuration so you could see
what happened
um let's assume we chose one equals one
meaning write a one to the tape
d1 equals r move the head right
transition to state e
so that's what happened to get from this
into this
through this state transition our next
decision for the transition
is we're in state e zero remember e
we're above zero
now we've used five states and two
symbols in the definition so for one
possibilities to choose the transition
to be the halting transition
alternatively we can choose from the
other stuff
yeah it seems counterproductive to
choose the halting transition as we have
a number of alternatives the problem is
we have no way of guaranteeing that any
of these alternatives will
result in a terminating machine
to output the machine in figure 11 as
one possibility and continue to search
for more
so this is i mean it's not even
partially generated right i think we
know already what the behavior of this
machine is going to be
the reason we can always ensure that the
generation of an end-state m-symbol
machine results in a machine which is
end state full meaning it
visits all states and m symbol full uses
all symbols is the strict monotonicity
for the
beaver function in other words we know
that it gets bigger
this justifies the above step in which
the halton transition
was not considered when searching for
that meaning it's yeah okay
it's not saying anything to
it's intuitively obvious that the
busybeaver function is monotonic about
the number of states and number symbols
sure i think nobody doubts that um
let's see if we can write the proof just
by reading the proposition
uh
let m be a k halting end state m symbol
turn machine with finite activity
then there is a case k halting n plus
one with one more state m symbol
targeting machine with
finite activity such that
all right let's see if we can come up
with a proof for that
i'm not sure it matters but just just
just like a thought exercise
uh so we can talk we can say
when the old machine was about to
transition to the halt state
um
i think we can actually construct
something that will
continue to do that transition as long
as there's ones
but then as soon as this one gets to a
zero it writes a one and it halts
i will loop back there do you see what
i'm saying
so we can just do like we can write like
a run to a zero and halt machine
with one more state see if that's what
that proof says
uh
yeah okay so pretty much yeah
all right so you run run to a one as
soon as you find a zero go to the whole
state
it doesn't matter whether it's left
right you can do it quickly cool
always good it's always good to do that
uh like do like a check like if you can
predict what's coming next you're you
understand something and a lot of times
you don't know whether you understand
something or not
um transformation is straightforward and
the method of increasing machine science
is highly unlikely to be any practical
use
so this gets into like this condition is
now not a condition that applies to
this is a condition that only applies to
the busy beaver problem not a condition
that applies to a generic
uh symmetry based reduction
of the turing machine space
hmm they've been unable to prove this
result can we prove the result
let's think about it let m be a k
halting turing machine with n states and
m symbols
uh for some k greater than one with
finite activity
greater than equal to one with finite
activity then there exists
a k holding m plus one
such that the activity and the
productivity are strictly greater given
one more symbol
oh yeah that is a lot harder
it was a lot harder
see
unfortunately we've been unable to prove
this result despite it seemed to be
obviously true how much time did you put
into it
um one of the things that i like and
like the uh
i think like donald knuth started it
he'd rate
problems with a difficulty rating from
zero to 50
based on how long it's going to take you
whereas like 50 or open problems
10 is something you can do in your head
20 is something you can do in 10 minutes
30 is something that's going to take
like a day
and 40 or something that's a good
research project for a semester
what is busy beaver 5 42.
finding some appropriate transformation
hence providing a truth uh proof of
conjecture 28.
um of course that doesn't
change the above thing about states
an even stronger result is desirable
here that we can guarantee that all
generated machines are exhaustive to do
so would require a result similar to
prop 27 but showing the strict
monotonicity of the busy beaver function
in terms of the number of transitions in
the machine
okay well so obviously if you if you add
another i mean if you add another state
you get if you have n states you get
another m transitions and if you add
another
uh
symbol you get n more transitions
but
what if you like take away two states
and add three symbols
so yeah the the the monotonicity on on n
plus m that's cute though
would that be a well that would be a
cool thing to prove you know i said
um it should be noted that we cannot
guarantee a generated machine will be
one halting
as we cannot guarantee that a partially
generated machine will always terminate
and so executing the machine may never
result in an opportunity to add a
halting transition
that's what i don't like about executing
the machine like i can look at the
machine i mean i guess if i know the
smaller busy beaver numbers i know how
many steps i have to execute it for
before i can say that it won't terminate
right
yes solving the halting problem for
little little machines using busy beaver
numbers
pretty cool right you know chayton's got
some crazy arguments about this kind of
stuff about like
why some busy beaver numbers are uh
we can know them and like which ones we
can't and he kind of says that
of this unknowable information you can
only get as much
unknowable information out of a system
as
axioms you put in uh which is
you know i have it's kind of fun like
like lay in bed for like 30 minutes and
think about that statement
and uh
you you you come up with
a kind of really deep philosophical
truth about that
is all math constructed on nothing
uh this all relativism true
relativism is not true because you can
prove that calm graph complexity is
universal
um i went through a column graph
complexity book and did some proofs in
it once
i really like uh
one of my favorite websites
you want to learn more about you want to
learn uh
you want to learn more about ai
you want to learn more truths about a.i
than than any
bullshit fast ai course where you
implement the latest and transformer
blah blah blah blah blah blah
this
this web page
one can prove that the better you can
compress the better you can predict
and being able to predict the
environment well
is key for you being able to act well
consider the sequence of of pi if it
looks random to you you can either
compress it nor predict the next digit
but if you realize that it's pi you can
compress the sequence and predict the
next
it's next digit um
mdl this is this is the deep truths of
of ai the rest of it is just
learning hip new frameworks
better compression requires
understanding
uh in some cute ways you can also
talk about how science is just a quest
for better compresses
we have all this data science comes out
these little cute formulas that tell you
how to predict patterns in the data
but science also has this
constraint that whatever
it discovers also has to be human
understandable
math has debates about this
what is a math proof is a math proof
something that makes the solution
intuitive to humans or is a math proof
something more like you'd find in cock
which is a rigorous proof that may be
completely unreadable to any human
me i'm definitely in the second camp and
i think explainability of ai is the
biggest
scam oh but how did the ai make the
decision
yeah you ever ask a human that question
oh but you can ask the human and the
human will give you an answer
nah the human's got a little part in
their brain robin hansen talks about
this he calls it the press secretary
that just spins total bullshit lies
when humans are asked why they did
something
um they did some experiments and split
brain people that just shows
the extent to which humans will bullshit
so that they can have a coherent
understanding of the world
and you think you're getting a real
truth about why the human made the
decision
we're now in a position to define the
process for generating machines hell
yeah
this will follow the same general
strategy of the tnf process
ah wow this actually looks very
implementable
all right who wants to implement that
god i haven't coded and coding's hard
you know i'm coded in a bit i just don't
feel as
like you know i coded like merge sort
and actually i coded merge sort really
stupidly
uh in that stream um
i don't know it's been nice to be coding
less lately
but hopefully we can write this
let's see i know you come here to see
the lightning fast coatings on the
keyboard well you know what
you're the wrong kind of person this is
philosophy chat
um but not stupid philosophy a lot of
philosophy
like i was uh
on camping once i was younger
i was like 21 and i like to talk about
like stupid like universe philosophy
kind of stuff like is the universe
analog or digital you know like the
kind of things you want to talk about
when you you first start smoking weed
and this guy was like
you don't know anything about that
like it's kind of a childish thing to
talk about
and at the time i don't think i agreed
with him but as i got older i did
the philosophy that that's much more
interesting to me is the philosophy
that's grounded in this kind of stuff
the philosophy that's grounded in these
deep mathematical truths
um that requires uh
years of studying before you can
understand them okay uh
so this is the tree normal form
yeah let's just write it from scratch
just for for enjoyability for all of you
we won't we won't try to adapt the old
code
all right we'll call it zany zoo dot pi
sorry about the noise
okay let's initialize the machine
with the tuple um
well
like another way to talk about that is
just
say one rb in a zero
so we can say like let's say machine
equals none times 10.
should we not do this in python who
wants to use haskell should we use
haskell
i'm sick of python
sorry everything's going to take me
forever and hassle you know i'm not
going to be able to do things fast
uh i don't think we need moan ads
okay so haskell we're going to want to
define a
type of a machine
uh
and what zero dextrous means
should we use maybe we'll use c plus
plus i mean part of the problem
is gonna be with writing this in python
is it's going to be slow
and like i just i found myself like you
saw even the way i started that i
started just thinking about it in terms
of uh
in terms of strings like do i want to do
7 billion string manipulations in python
not really
[Music]
um
all right let's say
transition
i don't really remember c plus plus
either i only know python
but i think we can muddle through with
this a whole bit better
um so let's actually call the states
integers
uh let's try to use the same terminology
that they use
uh okay this is the terminology
let generate function go
generate here we go uh
so we're going to have output int
direction they're technically bulls
but we'll say in new state
um we'll say into transition function
we're going to define n is 5 when n is 5
the transition function is n
uh by m sorry that isn't five and
two uh these aren't ants they are
struck transition
it seems right right
uh so that's the definition of a machine
this can be
private
uh yeah we don't need this to be a class
it could just be a function
generate
okay
step one so we want to initialize the
machine
to the tuple uh
let's just make a macro s
which takes in a state subtracts
that from it right say s sub
a
cross zero
um
oh i have to write the stupid ass tape
as well gotta write an infinite tape in
c
plus plus infinite tapes are easier to
write in high school
okay so this is going to be a
uh oh this isn't you can't do that
um class transition
sounds marxist i spell transition wrong
i think i did
no i didn't okay
[Music]
oh
this isn't what i want either
i want something that's going to allow
me to write this
say one
no magic instructor for initialization
okay so how do i do this
like a colon
yeah it's like that but then what do i
separate them with more colons
more commas we'll separate commas and
see if complaints
that work no
matching constructor oh we need an
initialization constructor
l equals um d equals zero
no move yeah we'll say d
is minus one
you know what better yet
should have i done it in haskell no if i
didn't have yeah i know i know haskell
is like much nicer at stuff like this
but like i didn't haskell we would have
been
grappling with bullshit for a long time
undeclared identifier
calling a private constructor all public
we like to share here
he's just not looking tape changes moves
and position integers
you know what you're saying
[Music]
uh that's step one step two
choose the b zero transition
well the first transition is obviously
going to be that
i'm smacking the microphone it's in the
computer
[Music]
i don't have i don't have another mic
sorry we've got a
poverty stream voice poverty stream
yeah you know what you guys are talking
about computer that's dangerously close
to keyboard
guess what guess what's going to happen
you all know what's going to happen
let's try it that's what happens
all right
oh it's banned do you like hammers oh
who likes hammers if you like hammers
check out hammer.wall
we already got three people who applied
to come work at hammer
um but they clearly didn't realize we're
only hiring for one role
which is founder i'm not the founder of
hammer
because i never want to start another
company
uh if you're looking for a job go apply
to comma
uh that's my hn shell
we only do the twitch stream as a funnel
for hiring
because we are illegitimate and we're
duping you guys because we're on the
side of collaboration with
i'd never do that
subs are better people than non-subs
it's true glad
glad to see all you subs and joining it
yeah bye plebs
um yeah you can waste your channel
points but let me tell you about channel
points they eventually run out subs are
forever
okay
choose the b zero transition satisfying
one of the conditions below and add this
transition
to m
uh
i mean i feel like i want to enumerate
these all in a loop
like there's not too many of them
transition
output can be zero or one direction
is left and new state can be a
so i guess we want to try this direction
can be either no direction is always
left
but this can be zero or one
or it can also be since n is greater i
don't understand why this has to be a
special case but
we will we will trust the authors of the
paper
we are simply following
their will
position can be zero or one new state is
c
and this can be l or r so there's five
there's uh eight choices in step two
that code's obviously not right you have
to pick one
we can look
okay execute m on the blank input
until m is known to be irrelevant
or a bound on the number of execution
steps is exceeded
really
this is lame crap
what how do i bound the number of
execution steps
i don't like this paper anymore this is
just tree normal form
with like two extra steps added in
thank you for all your new subscribers
we'll turn it off again but guys
do we have to talk again today about
quality
i mean subs are low quality tonight
don't make me sad
hey serious quick chat time
um why do you guys watch this channel
especially when i do stuff like this
like it's fine when i'm ranting
about you know things that anybody can
have an opinion on but
one of these days i really am going to
make like a quiz right
and the quiz is going to include
questions like here's a small tarring
machine
how many steps does it run for until it
halts
and if you can't answer that after
following through this far we kick you
out of the class
oh that'd be so nice that's what we're
gonna do at college man
that's what we're gonna do at my new
college
every semester if you don't know shit
you get kicked out
doesn't help you be a better programmer
look at my mediocre ass
programming boys
sometimes i program well i don't know
i'm like second competition programming
for for a bit maybe i'll get into it
again but
whenever the code comes around all right
step three so we gotta
execute m on the blank input
so we need to write the turing machine
execution engine
uh we should write a class tape and
implement that
uh i mean so tape is really very
similar to vector except here all right
we're
just implementing two vectors uh class
tape
public what is it like operator
yeah it's this
[Music]
i think we can just implement it as two
factors
you know what maybe it would be a better
place we all just turned on no script
sorry for using stl classes i know i'm
pathetic
all right um
if all greater than or equal to zero
uh if
forward dot size
is less than l forward resize
l return
[Music]
forwards of l else
minus l minus one l equals l minus one
minus l minus one so that times minus
one into one
subtract one from that yeah that gets me
what i want uh i'll just change this to
backward here
compile of course not non-crash over
refrigerant cannot bind temporary type
ah
can i not use vector do i have to just
write it
because it's a 10 i mean you see why
it's a temporary type right
i actually made it a
all right is this this too is this too
ballsy for people
it might be ballsy man i don't know
seems ballsy
what no
oh they're gonna value type is this a
const oh good no it's not const
oh yes good oh that should work though
what no i put it without data
non-const l value reference to type int
cannot bind to a temporary type
oh maybe that i'm doing it by reference
let's test tape quickly
all right so we expect t sub 0 to return
zero
segmentation fault
oh fine
what but i resized it
well i guess we need a value type
that's all right oh a forward size
is less than l plus one
zero cool um so let's check the tape at
55.
uh let's set the tape at 55 work work
work work work all right sweetheart
oh let's just check it at minus 55 tim
high quality shit get it boys
we made a tape
[Music]
got rich off a mixtape
you should listen to drake just to fuck
with copyright filter
since i want speeds and i try to avoid
branches
i think the uh branch protector will get
that one fine
do you have an easy way i guess i could
call resize but who knows what that's
doing internally
i don't technically need that if state
well actually no i do need that if
statement
because otherwise it'll resize it to
shrink
okay um execute m on the blank input
okay
let's execute m so we'll say cs equals
state a which is current state
um and cp
current pointer zero
uh so we're gonna say if
no not f we're gonna get uh
t t equals t f
sub what state are we currently in our
current state
times the current on the other current
pointer but the tapes of the current
pointer
um and wait that's not a tt that's
actually a transition
so maybe we can just use it directly
uh okay so single type
ttf dot
uh output so we're gonna say t sub cp
equals gtf output we're going to say
cp plus equals ttf direction
i need to do my directions yeah
and if
well actually no we can just say cs
equals
ttf dot new state
if cs equals equals minus one
that should be a time machine runner
right
that do it right
okay well something
cool that holds great
uh it obviously falls because we didn't
have any uh
okay if we have an undefined input
well how can i call it undefined
let's say new state equals minus two
um
actually we're actually going to say
direction is zero as well
we don't actually want to add anything
okay
so that means we gotta define the state
uh
i won't be able to set those things okay
choose a new transition
for m as follows if m is n stateful
and m symbol fall and
the thingy is not zero dextrous oh god i
don't know what that means
guys
we were talking a comma about adding a
uh restriction to the model
which says that the model's output must
be self-consistent
and
we talked about this for a bit and it's
very
true that a model that makes very
self-consistent like temporally
consistent
outputs um
all models that are good do this but not
all models that do this
are good models it's the same way about
you guys talking about how i
move around from insert mode into
non-insert mode you know
that doesn't make you a good programmer
studying that stuff will never ever
make you a good programmer stop talking
about it
nobody gets good by studying vim
shortcuts
you get good by programming for years
and years
and years decide what you want to write
program it
you'll just get better at the tools
nobody told any good talks about tools
it won't make you more productive it
really won't
you watched me code this right it's 88
lines
most of my time was spent thinking most
of my time was not spent
fumbling around with my editor if most
of your time is being spent fumbling
around with your editor
uh
i wish somebody told me this years and
years and years ago
you give me the ratiest editor on the
most beat ass
computer with the worst keyboard and
i'll beat you
the stuff doesn't make you good
okay
if m is n stateful and m
symbol full
and m union
a transition to the halt state is not
zero dextrous okay i think we're not
going to get around figuring out what
zero dextrous means
uh add that new state to the machine
so let's write the add the
add the halt state
thought output equals we always output a
one
um we always transition
to the right and
our new state is
state underscore halt
do
if it's not zero deck stress
okay um
i think we're gonna need to write
some recursive stuff here
because like for all of these things we
want
all of them not just one
choice means our machine are
dexterous or right-handed
note that in step four they really don't
uh define this very well regime is
unstateful
and uh m symbol full
well that one i can get a whole lot
better
okay so we can ask a question about the
machine
uh
this is annoying we actually have to ask
we have to
say how many states have we seen
um you also need to track
symbol scene
i think this is right right
uh then we do not actually want that to
be zero we want it to be minus
[Music]
cool
there's like better ways to do this in
more modern say
[Music]
actually
that's not exactly what we want to do we
don't actually really want to halt there
um
before we set the state
and actually i guess before we do
anything
we can check to see
run step
that'll actually halt right
ttf dot news um
i'm upset with the comments well i read
in a page you do security contracting i
got on a page the earth was flat man
yo you should check out this page it
says global warming is a hoax promoted
by the international zionist conspiracy
theorists full trash boys
no i just don't know what zero dextrous
means unfortunately
it doesn't seem that important though
check def 23 on page 15.
all right
oh cool thank you i don't know why my
search didn't find that
i'll leave it as a to to-do for now
because we have to address a more
fundamental problem
about how we choose
uh like we have
choices here
i don't understand step five really
either but
i mean
how do you actually like run this
i i feel like i almost have to like like
copy the machine
add that one state and then
redo the procedure right because look at
what i mean look i have the same problem
up here
right
when the machine's created you could put
it online
and it's going to generate uh
links about how you can make four
thousand dollars in one month using this
one weird trick after you buy my ebook
guide for only 28.99
and then i'm gonna sit here and i'm
gonna rake in the dollars
that's right because money is going to
make you happier
you really think they would show you all
those ads on television
if the products weren't going to make
you happy go out get money
buy products consume product
will be so happy and fulfilled in your
life
for a bit and then you consume more
product but don't worry as long as you
keep consuming product
america promises you a nice life the
advertisers promise you a nice life they
say all the time in their advertisements
[Music]
what do i do about this all right
like what do i do about this isn't this
like
this is easy in prologue i think i think
this is easy in prologue
because it's a logic programming
language fucking prologue man
i don't really know what prologue is but
i have an idea that you can
you can do this kind of thing very
easily in prologue
you guys see the thing that i'm asking
for right i mean here well we'll
we'll we'll write it out stupidly um
for n and n equals zero
and less than n n plus plus
same thing with m
uh for d in
oh this is a little annoying thing about
d that i didn't really consider
can i say something like
call
oh
expected variable name or this in
lambda listy
oh sweet okay
um well it's doing something
oh i guess we have to set the state
ttf.output equals m ttf.direction
equals d uh but everyone sees why this
isn't actually right
and not what we want we want to like
kind of fork every time
right uh
we wanna
apparently n cubed i mean those numbers
are small
um love that syntax by the way beautiful
beautiful syntax
like i wanna i wanna spawn a new
uh
yeah like i want to spawn a new thread
from that location
every time
you know spawn
after each one of those i want to spawn
i guess that one doesn't uh
that one doesn't haul
step six is go to step three
okay what's the easiest way to write
this
see i mean they really are threats right
so so if i wanted
to go crazy i could actually spawn a new
thread in that location
i would have to make copies we'd have to
make
copies
the zero dextrous thing is not a big
deal it's just going to like reduce the
space a little bit
let's try to read the prologue and see
how they did it
i think prologue is a language that's
like designed to be run in this way
though i think that's kind of
what prologue is
we should have a stream where we learn
prologue
well if someone buys me a mic
and puts it in an amazon locker send a
mic to an amazon locker in the east
village in new york city
i will go pick it up and then i'll have
a mic for the streams
no i mean you'll be a hero to the
streamers who don't like hearing the mic
noises
you had an exam with prologue
you can't set things to uh
huh maybe you can
i mean that's okay so one thing we could
do here
is we could refactor the transition
thing to allow sets
but that's not exactly right either
because would the sets be
a cross or would the sets be a plus
and this whole thing has to look kind of
like a
uh i mean how do i choose which one to
execute i guess i could implement a
priority queue
a priority q for the total number of
steps the machine has executed
yeah i think that's probably right okay
we have to put the machines in a
priority queue
uh oh
crap though to have to put the tape with
it
it's not just the machine i gotta also
put the tape
that means i gotta write a fucking copy
constructor
[Music]
okay let's
class machine
um and the machine has this transition
function
machine m
actually we don't we can make machine m
but we're also gonna need to make
a standard priority queue of machine
this is hard boys it was supposed to be
easy ms
dot push m
you
okay
let's just see if that compiles
include qe
forward definition of matching
okay that's an okay thing to complain
about
um okay we make this a function on
machine
no actually we'll go even further with
that we'll just say um
i'll call this a
is full
return
and
so now we can just change this to m dot
uh
is full
i don't know what any of that means
variable has incomplete type machine
machine like a keyword or some crap
we'll call it a tm for a time machine
better not good can't use machine
i didn't like tm either oh probably more
because i put these parentheses here
this isn't
python what language do you think you're
coding in
but it also still seems to have issues
with maschine
t machine yeah that's a good name for it
we'll call it the t
machine it's not just any machine it's a
t machine
and t machine has the same as this
machine
okay machine it is t machine only
sounded good when i couldn't have
machine
you know like hammer.lol sounded good
when i couldn't have hammer.com
um oh okay so actually the main thing
it's complaining about
here is that i didn't implement the uh
wouldn't implement the comparison
constructor
without the comparison instructor how do
we know who's better than other people
actually
um i'm just gonna make this a
run function in the machine machine
[Music]
run
we don't actually need ttf we can get
that
again in the run function i don't even
need
this m dot because we are m
returns c cs equals
i'm not wrong
one is a private member of machine
everything should be public private
okay well that's a more understandable
thing
uh steps equals zero
uh steps plus plus and then we'll just
do comparison on
steps
um
less than operator c
plus plus comparison operator
if i had hammer it would have already
found what i was looking for because
hammer always just knows things you know
hammer it reads your mind
return if m
dot steps less than
oh sorry steps less than m
invalid operands to
binary expression but i defined it now
machines have an ordering
can i put less than
i need to put less than where do i have
a typo
oh i probably need a const here
or i need something like bull const
operator
line 56 typo where
i don't have amazon if somebody
dropships in amazon
invalid comparison to binary expression
const machine con's machine
between that and that for const
i think you're right yeah see
blue spec you're a smart guy
all right we're making some progress
boys
progress
it's a good thing this wasn't haskell if
we were trying to do this in haskell
we i've given up already if this was
python i would have written some
egregious copyright hacks
and we would be done but it would take
27 years to finish running
okay good we have
eight machine
um let's just write a quick
[Music]
check
hmm okay so i think then we want to just
say
or pop m equals ms
pop
let's actually just confirm while ms.i
is greater than zero
ms.pop m equals ms.pop
and then let's just print let's actually
make sure i made copies
void oh
top oh that's a const reference
the hell kind of crap is this
why doesn't pop return the thing
kind of useless priority queue is this
no viable overloaded equals
i'm not happy about this it's because i
have to write a copy constructor don't i
cannot convert argument of incomplete
type void
to machine to the first argument
the implicit all right all right we knew
we'd have to write this
didn't i complain about having to write
those
um copy
operator
copy assignment operator
looks like this it returns
a machine pointer
this dot cs equals m dot cs this dot cp
equals m dot cp
um this dot steps equals m dot steps
um t f equals m dot t f oh yeah that's
going to go over well
probably have to write this
and i don't know how it's going to take
this one tape equals m dot tape
or t equals n dot t i think we're going
to have to also write a copy constructor
for tape
candidate function not viable cannot
convert
argument of incomplete type void
oh it's also complaining about that but
this argument has typed const tape
but the method is not marked const
all right we'll write the copy
constructor for tape as well
let's see if it compiles
take t of four equals t dot forward
backwards t dot backward copy
constructor
on vector
okay using assignment operator
this argument has type
const
oh
hmm oh i don't want discounts there
yeah were you guys talking about that
i'm glad to see there's a hype train
going on thank you people i appreciate
your support
and i hate when you say dumb things so
support more and say dumb things less
and everybody wants
um control reaches the end of non-void
function return this
try and reference this
return draft this you think this
okay cool thank you
nice to see somebody knows uh
remember reference base type and is not
in a structure
or union
copy this one is that good
um canada function not viable
cannot convert argument of type
incomplete void
oh because i'm still using pop it's not
pop it's top
yeah okay member reference base type
in is not a structure or union
[Music]
about that
okay so it's doing something but it
isn't actually working
because that's not calling the copy
constructor it wouldn't return all
ones if it was calling the copy
constructor
all right because i'm asking for the
output which the output is here zero one
zero one zero one zero one
so it's not calling the copy constructor
it's just using the last one
um
why doesn't push make a copy
well you know what i can put a print f
in the copy constructor or maybe it does
and i'm just not copying the transition
table
um
oh okay we're making a lot of copies
damn that's a lot of copies boys where
do we make these copies
not there here
well there oh i guess we're i guess i
mean maybe we're not even making them
here
yeah okay we're not making them there we
only make them further down and we're
actually making
way too many um
assignment op is not a copy constructor
did you also write a copy constructor
probably not
oh you're right oh you're right this is
not a copy constructor this is just an
assignment
oh yeah okay this is stupid
um
do i even need this i i meant to write a
copy constructor
i don't even need this and now it does
what i want
that scares me it now does what i want
now that i removed
that extra code
better now
i'm not doing github review
okay cool where do you think i made a
coffee constructor
i don't see one but this seems good
well actually no there's one thing
that's not complete here and that's the
tape
yeah yeah usually don't even the copy
constructor so
when i'm copying the tape am i actually
copying the underlying
vectors
it's working that's good
so now we know what to do when we want
to quote unquote spawn
we can just say ms.push m
all right it should work
uh why can't i call push
oops i'm in ms.com
i got it though
i'm calling ms.pushm there the types
haven't changed
oh i created a new m that's stupid
um
sorry this kind of crappy code i should
kind of refactor that
okay okay yeah yeah yeah use a real
editor do something that can do this
with one click yeah
yeah yeah i know i know that feels
all right you're happy
all right well it does something
so i'm putting all the machines in a
priority queue every time we create a
new machine we add to the priority queue
the priority queue is sorted by the
number of steps the machines have taken
we can actually add that here
they've all taken no steps
i guess we yeah we add all the possible
transitions
um
only if a state is undefined does it end
up there
wait how does my
has my priority queue have negative size
oh
okay it didn't add any transitions great
but you got you got a lot of
stupid ass languages like c plus plus
what call it integer overflow
oh i did i remember that on a stream
once
um right you're already cute i remember
i remember that on a stream once where
i was screaming about what a bad
language it is like what kind of a
language
has shitty numbers like that like
what kind of language let that happen
you know would you let your kids program
in a language like that
okay um if mm is full
i'm sure m is not fall
has it not what
oh maybe we kind of want to say else
and then push all right
okay something
is that really the best thing in the
priority queue
or something as aliasing
there's 47 things in the priority queue
why is it returning one with that many
steps oh unless
okay do we really want inverted priority
queue
should probably give you the biggest or
the smallest
a largest
all right let's first like try it for
this how many machines are there
um
oh it shouldn't actually break if it
halts
ah we'll say okay first off why did i
make mm.run return true with the halt
i'm going to make it return
false if it halts and true if it should
continue
and then we don't break but only if the
step actually runs do we add it back to
the queue
add back to q if
no pulp more
run please
step four to do right now
okay it's doing something now
look at it marching along the tape
oh they just keep tarring and tarring
and tarring
so
let's overwhelm my computer ah
again
okay so it seems like pretty quickly
we get to four nine
four and actually for every machine that
halts
let's add it to a halting machines
um
m
oh my vector has std
okay so of it looks like
this works pretty well i mean we're
beyond the number of steps what is busy
beaver
3 oh god why don't i use my own
wikipedia and not be exposed to this
bullshit
yeah my wikipedia
media my wiki
so we know that we've set n to
3 and m to 2 so i would expect
yeah so 21 is there so as soon as we get
to 21 over here
you can see where we actually transition
wow c plus plus so fast c plus plus is
so
fast but so it looks like
of all the machines we enumerate 457 of
them halt
and 4494 don't halt
and we can do something else too
let's just quickly uh
we'll say bbn equals zero um
bbn equals uh max
oh well equals uh mm dot steps
um just i want max
i don't i'm gonna have to import
something for max aren't i
oh you're where's max oh do you mean
standard max oh that's declared here
hmm 17. it's almost 21.
uh yeah we got a machine that runs for
17 steps
now let's up into four and see what we
get
depending on undefined state a lot
how do we print that out well actually
whenever we get here so that's not
okay
it's got some machines that run for
eight so it's like trying them all in
like a breath first search kind of way
this is the total number of halted
machines this is the total number of
machines in general
you have to print every time either it's
kind of a lot of printing
yeah i don't know it doesn't work for
three and two yet so we can we can fix
it
now none of these machines are going to
halt it's continuing it's running it's
running non-halting machines
of which there are this many thousands
okay uh so things i worry about are we
actually making a copy of the tape
we might not be um
if you have a class with a vector inside
of it and you make a copy of that class
is there one vector or two vectors
to do learn c plus
or is there some reason we just didn't
get
the one that we're looking for
that definitely worked
let's um
declare identifiers
move semantics
no it's not for n equals 17.
it's trying it for three comma two and
we're getting the longest any machine is
running
uh a number of steps that it's taking is
um
oh well okay i mean there's a tiny bug
here
where
[Music]
i think if we just say ms.pop that fixes
that
because the last one we pushed is
actually
i mean actually if we want to be more
explicit about it we can just do this
no it's always the last one
we run the last
pushed machine
right now
oh look that got rid of a lot of uh that
made my code so much faster boys
we got more speed you thought as soon as
i add in the zero dextrous
check we'll have an unbelievable amount
of speed
cheapest plus so fast
okay
let's
now
why am i only getting 17
the answer i should be getting according
to my
very secure and high quality local copy
of wikipedia
is 21.
you know check over two by two maybe
that's easier to think about
three with some real junk here
oh because i didn't write it to work for
it did actually
oh no i didn't these ones are not
included
this is only if n is greater than two
it's actually if n is greater than or
equal to three so we'll just copy from
the paper
that's what was breaking when i said
into two
sorry that's again not moving
six okay good so it's working for
n equals two it's just not working
for n equals three but it's fast
so it can be forgiven you know sometimes
if you come up with the wrong answer but
you do it really really fast
now you're a terrible person don't ever
be wrong
is there anything wrong here
maybe i'm getting my okay so i didn't do
the zero dextrous
check
i don't think it matters though
let's just think about what we're doing
okay so every time
we come upon an undefined state we add a
machine
which replaces that undefined state with
every possible state transition
both possible directions and every
possible output
create that machine no reason to leave
since we're still going to run it
the other alternative actually what's
probably better to write here
is just continue right if i just
continue through
the loop
no machine to run
right now right
all right gives you the same answer
actually behave slightly differently
though which doesn't exactly make sense
but like give me different numbers here
but i kind of feel like that's more
correct right because continue
gonna go back up here get me the top
machine pop it
uh so on and so forth
okay um if it's full
now maybe is full maybe i'm not getting
the definitions of these things right
okay what does end state full mean
and stateful if
the cardinality of q
equals n
maybe step four matters
oh sorry this one if the cardinality of
m which i don't totally understand
uh oh basically
if your only choice right now would be
to add if there's only
one unassigned thing it's obviously and
there's no other halting one
uh add the halting one i think that's
just a speed up i don't think that
should be a requirement
um let me see if i did anything else
particularly stupid
all right there's a question of maybe
we're not making a copy of the tape
um we can check this let's just write a
quick test for this
machine m machine m2
um we know the first
i'm gonna call it t i should really call
it tape tape is what i call the class
so too late for that
okay we get 1 1 which is what we expect
and if we do that before we do it we get
0 0 okay i haven't taken any steps yet
now machine mm2 equals mn
we expect these tapes to be different
the tapes are different okay never mind
it works
so it is copying the tape
kraken dmp thank you for subscribing
we appreciate every subscriber even the
ones that i don't read out
on this stream some people get lucky all
right
um it's copying the tape
uh
there's definitely four there four there
let's think about what's happening if
we're not hitting this undefined thing
[Music]
um
yeah okay we run
push it to the thing
otherwise it's halting and we take it
off
and we check
yeah this code's not bad it's actually
pretty clean code
is bad
okay who can find the bug
who can find
i really don't think it's the zero
dextrous thing
because that's just excluding machines
we're checking more machines than we
have to
if we were checking uh less machines
than we had to
for some reason we're not getting the
machine that's
that's uh the busy beaver for three
we do get the one that's the busy beaver
for two but we don't get it for three
what if we do like 2 comma 3 what do we
get 26 is that 26
well again it should be 38
so that one's not working right either
um okay these are all simple
types except
for tape but we know that that's working
okay because we tested it
um with these eight possible starting
machines
we're initializing that tuple
correctly
execute m on the blank input until m is
known to be irrelevant
or the bound on the number of execution
steps is exceeded output m and halts
uh so that's what we do here
an undefined combination of
the state and input is found which is
what we do here
choose a new transition as follows if
m is n state full and m symbol full
let's be more aggressive with this
let's maybe we did the definition of
this wrong
um there's another simpler way to define
this
and we can actually just say it's just
states
scene we can define it out here and this
is actually also going to be faster to
run
um symbol scene sub m
and then fur is full we can just change
it to this
and we say uh s
date scene
uh sub cs equals one
now it shouldn't actually be cp this
should just be
um
symbol scene sub zero equals one
scene a and zero
and here we'll say
symbol scene sub ttf
output i like this one
oh so i don't want to delete all that i
did want to leave these in there
great now it gives me one
hmm i'm okay that's already when i'm in
an undefined state
um is full
is about a transition that seems correct
it seems like a lot of them are halting
really fast now
because many more giving me is full
i guess
um
i'm still not really understanding i
mean maybe it's a cross product
if it's seen every state and every
symbol in that state
will that ever happen
all right well i think i think the
problem is that we're getting the
definition of this wrong
so let's be more careful
m stateful if
the cardinality of q
equals n
that just means that we've defined
a ton of machines are halting they've
been in every state
and it just says oh i've been in every
state why do i need to keep running
um i've been in every state and i've
seen every symbol
now it's time to halt but that's not
right
the other halting transition in the
generate process is actually much more
interesting i think
all right let's remove that one
that's only
let's just let's do this
that should work right well nothing's
ever going to halt
but we can add in step four
if the cardinality of the machine
basically if we have
that's interesting that it doesn't even
run the machine
um
i got one called card uh
f tf sub n
dot new state
uh is state undefined
if mm dot card
equals n times m minus one
and an order operation should be fine
there
then
uh add a faulting to the last
missing states
you have mmotl
a little redundant from above
uh that's probably stupid way to write
it
but we can do it it's fine
and steps
all right still no lock
this ever happened
am i getting crazy big numbers for that
doesn't make any sense does it
can't be greater than six
ah compiler you should tell me when i do
stupid things like that
all right still doesn't work
now half the machine's halt
but they only seem to take one step
that can't be right
it doesn't even make sense
oh well so this actually shouldn't
really be
here can we do this here
matter
okay it definitely doesn't make sense
that it's giving me one
that that makes less than no sense how
how are all these machines halting
yet they've allegedly only taken one
step that's a scam
okay so those are
see they've already taken five steps
how could it be returning one
i'm on the fives in the priority queue
it doesn't make sense
there's twos and threes already i guess
none of them
have to halt
okay this doesn't make sense right if
i'm at five on the priority queue and i
popped a machine off the priority queue
there
how does it have only taken one step
it's not calling this constructor right
all right chat's getting stupid
what is it one
else okay the way that we end up in that
else
is we take a step
to a machine that we just added a
halting state too but we only ever add
the halting state
and this should only happen once
now it's also showing that half the
machine's halt
what's chaitin's constant for the target
machine because you guys should all know
it's constant they can't be one it
doesn't make sense
very upsetting
okay b5 e1
something in the run
could it be setting steps to zero
somehow
who sees the bug who sees the bug
oh man oh
god
it was an underflow in the state scene
array
what a savage language really what a
savage language oh look it's going to be
21 now
oh we did it 21 is the right answer
right hell yeah
21 all right let's check if we can get
38. so you see i'm setting two
from two and three from three all right
38 fingers crossed
no 38 we got 26 okay that one doesn't
work yet
check this one six that one works okay
cool so increasing n
seems to work 21 will we get 107 if we
do this yeah it's okay if it takes a
long time oh wow it's gonna take a
real long time
no bug life you know
well we implemented that anyway which we
were supposed to implement
now we can try the new mm is full maybe
it will still work
no it only gives us 7.
so we don't really understand how to
write that yet
i do want that up here
okay
yeah chad's really low quality
oh sorry too let's see if we can work
with this one
i don't know many symbols don't really
make sense to me
oh i know it doesn't work
uh because we have to iterate through
symbols here
not states
all right isn't that what it says in the
paper
no just simple choice is only zero or
i one this doesn't matter if it's the
first one right
i don't know why we only get 26 there
we do get 21 there and that's what
matters and if we increase this to this
we get huge uh
big explosion
okay now we can start pruning
now that we have something that works
it's going to run this enormous number
of time machines
why'd no one read the paper you know
you're all at homework
nobody does their homework no more class
you know here i felt bad for only
reading some of the paper
you all should feel terrible about
yourselves
read the fucking paper you know like who
tried
you know what and some of you did and
some of you did and actually i have a
feeling
and this is this is again internet
tragedy of the comments
i have a feeling that there's some of
you who actually tried to read the paper
and you tried and you didn't understand
everything that was said i read it i
didn't understand everything that was
said either
and you're staying quiet trying to learn
while people who are you know
didn't try to read the paper were like
oh i'm too stupid for that
they're also too stupid and i want to
shut up
well i didn't know i didn't know there
was homework oh my dog ate my homework
bro travis collaptic got yelled at for
saying this an uber but one day you're
going to wake up and you're going to
realize
that all your successes and all your
failures in life are you they're not the
other person
you know they're not all this guy off
only at this opportunity
oh if only i got to shut up you know
real talk
oh i wanted or i wanted or i couldn't i
wanted or i couldn't
oh you're making excuses to man god
god's going to judge the shit out of you
you know every person who doesn't treat
you like god is doing your disservice
you know every person who buys into your
excuses just lets excuses go in the
world
all right let's see we can cut down on
here
all right let's understand zero dextrous
you know that's sad it's sad that they
oh you're like the motivational speeches
some people want those kind of tough
love speeches you know how it wasn't
rocky man
the problem with self-help is if you
need a self-help book to be motivated
that's not like it's not
lasting you're just addicted to
self-help i i guess the same thing is
true for anyone who thinks they need
drugs to be motivated or anything like
that
like no it's not it's not easy
it doesn't just come easy who thinks
it's all oh some people just are they're
able to be motivated they just have a
different brain chemistries
no it's hard for everybody a lot of
people just don't talk about
sir john duke thank you for gifting subs
um
we'll switch back to we'll switch back
to non-subscriber only uh
you know some people like semi-things
and uh
they're like oh george no i've never
said to anyone before but you're my idol
or shit like that like
i don't care you know what i would care
about
if you like sent me something that like
taught me something and
was interesting right i would care i
would care more if you didn't send me
anything and you spent your time like
learning something
learning a skill i i don't care i don't
want to be famous fuck being famous man
famous people are losers man you know
how i know they're losers they're all
drug addicts and they all kill
themselves when they're 27 right
oh but i want to be famous man you know
what the outcomes look like for famous
people
not great i'm gonna be famous i want the
world to know more
shit like real real facts about things
it's hot in here
all right i think we're gonna draw it
today we're gonna get it to the point
where we can
have it do busy beaver four so right now
we can do busy beaver three
um but
i think this is actually supposed to
execute early though
like it's not supposed to run them all
um maybe what i've written now is is
tree normal form
but let's implement zero deck stress
so basically i think we add it to the
list only if it's zero dextrous
some of you guys are very good i really
appreciate who caught the const bug in c
plus i appreciated who brought up where
the definition of zero dextrous was
of course i lost it
so i think we just don't want to push
the machine
if uh yeah
oh i think there's another bug here
too
this is actually spamming over all the
states
should i mean like i really have to make
a copy of the machine here
hopefully that makes a copy
great now i have even more
oh no i'm only setting no no it's fine
never mind you have to do that
it's not a challenger game for
programming it's a math problem
trying to solve a math problem you know
um if you will allow me to indulge in a
moment of self-pity
uh you know why am i not doing this at a
university
all right why am i streaming this kind
of shit on twitch
uh i don't know some ways i don't really
have the
i guess i don't have the
conscientiousness
uh to like apply to a university and
work in a lab
where i could uh i could do this
um you know part of it is i could scream
about how the university systems cocked
um how you know they're going to ask me
to to to write an essay about diversity
and not questions about math
which i'll immediately say wow this
institution is a bullshit institution
and i don't want any part of it
um yeah
hello i'm in new york you know
it'd be nice oh no the corona virus is
going on we can't go we can't go
anywhere oh that's right oh yes that's
the corona virus
um i've set up a straw man you're right
you're right no that's what i said like
if you let me indulge in a moment of
self-pity i don't know if that's true
i don't know if that's true maybe that's
just something i construct in my head
uh it's probably something i constructed
in my head to get out of
like like it's not like i could show up
right because i have tried this before
and this doesn't work
um i'm not sure to say that you know
they're they're correct and you're going
to write an essay about diversity i
don't actually know about that
um but
it's not like i can just like show up in
a math lab
right like a group of people who are
actually
i mean it's a cool problem it's not i
don't know
um like like like a working group to
kind of
kind of do this with uh
if i wanted this if i wanted to build it
online i probably could
um this is not the platform for it but
again this comes down to my lack of kind
of conscientiousness right
uh if i wanted to build a proper
place where we could get together and
work on this you'd have to make the
barrier to entry really high
um not just sit down and click the
twitch stream button
largely as an excuse so i can talk to
myself
um yeah you have to be working on a phd
i don't want to do this for six years
look i got a month in new york i
actually think
with a group of people like you know a
bunch of let's say three smart people
uh in the right sort of setting for for
a month you know i'd be excited about it
so it would spill over into two
uh we could solve this problem and it
would be kind of fun and it would just
be like something to do and i guess
i mean i wish the world was more like
that
uh do i talk to myself casually yeah but
i don't verbalize
i'm talking myself in my head right
inner monologue
some people say they don't have an inner
model i wonder
i wonder we found the philosophical
zombies
so that's actually step five
and step three is defining a depth first
search procedure and not a breath for a
search procedure
um
which
uh have i thought about recurs center i
i think i
looked into them once and found
my experience with
um that's not exactly true
i don't know my experience with a lot of
those kind of things
is i don't know about recur center
but at least uh like hacker spaces and
stuff
is it's a lot of people doing very
shallow projects
um and then there's people working on
deeper projects but they're kind of
inaccessible for various reasons
and then there's the kind of people who
show up to anything and make the whole
place miserable
um some of them are taken over by those
kind of people
you know the kind of
[Music]
know nothing let's check my private
wikipedia for a definition of that
huh
in a weird way it's kind of it's kind of
apt
but you know you guys know what i mean
um
so all right i guess i guess it's kind
of i guess it's kind of q a time
um we'll do a little q a and then we'll
we'll try to
it solves it solves busy beaver uh three
if we let it run i'm sure it would solve
for but it doesn't do it very
efficiently because we got to code the
zero dextrous check
um
no it's not it's only supposed to
iterate over in minus one and one
um use s-l-i
dot d-o to do q a
let me create an account my first name
is bob
my last name is boberson my email is
bob boberson
uh no my email is geohot plus bobber
gmail.com my password is you know
that and my role is
i work as on internal comms
quick event
if they make you create a slido account
my event is ready okay come join my
slido event
people let's slide oh
oh sweet no one had to oh yes all right
showing q a all right well let's see if
i can create a a
a q a question if i go to slido
and i type in the number
type your question do you like
fish
oh yeah it works oh do you like fish oh
that's a good question i'm gonna upload
that
wait can other people upload it oh all
right i say
all right guys anything inappropriate
ends up on here
we're exiting it out and you know what
it's it's it's uh
you know what i'm gonna minimize this
and i'm gonna trust you guys
to moderate we'll just leave that there
you can find the slido
and i'm going to trust you guys to to
have
sanitized the responses
um and if people say inappropriate
things the stream's over
welcome to you know what's that one
light goes out they all go out
that's not what i'm meant for
there's a word for it
any turing machine is
zero dextrous if there are n
transitions of the form
and all n transitions are of the form
0 r i see
that just seems really easy to implement
what is zdex
um
you know i kind of regret making this a
two-dimensional array i just made it a
one-dimensional array i could have saved
a lot of code
um
okay so first let's check if it's valid
new state uh
good rates
are not equal to stay undefined
tf sub n dot m dot uh
what is that oh no never mind so that's
actually i don't even have to iterate
through the ends
i just check for zero here
uh dot direction not equal to one
right uh if
direction not equal to one rat equals
false break
if not
i think we want the izzy dexterous or
the not is z dexterous
not mm dot is z dex
okay that looks like less um
so that gets us to
two six six one two seven seven three
great it saved us a whole
oh what a junk optimization
um
okay if m is end stateful
and m symbol fall
are the questions sad
i you know the questions are sad
well you know what maybe maybe we'll do
tomorrow's stream and tomorrow scream
stream only subscribers can watch
oh yeah buddy that's what i'm talking
about you know
only subscribers can watch we all think
that doesn't work
yeah yeah that's right
and to build up the subs first no i want
everybody to get a notification
and then like you guys can all be here
for the warm-up song tomorrow and then
after the warm-up song i'm gonna be
subs only
now this one doesn't go on youtube this
this one's the one where i tell you the
real secrets to learning how to program
you just gotta subscribe see i'm lying
to you people
you know a real sad truth about the
world man
people think a lot of people a lot of uh
you'll hear you'll hear uh
you know like like like poor people say
this that kind of stuff like it's a
system man or being oppressed by the
system
and i agree with them um they're being
oppressed by the system they didn't
build the system it's unfair
uh what you realize about like the rich
people and the quote-unquote elites
is they're also being oppressed by the
system now you can
assign them a bit more blame because all
they built the system but they really
didn't
right mullet built the system
they were supposed to do something about
it i agree that they had more
responsibility to do something about it
but they live in the same exact terrible
you know systems that everybody else
does and people think they can change
them but they really can't
uh i don't know
i'm a revolution kind of guy i don't
think you uh
you can't change the system just build a
better system
and like my system is open and inclusive
and everyone wants to come to the new
system and come to a new system
oh look it's too important in the world
man if only i could hit home runs like
babe ruth if only i got luck like that
i mean so that's an it's an interesting
thought that like if we add that one
back in
and may generate
all correct machines
just not run them
right we may still be generating the
machine that executes
for uh
right so i mean an interesting thing to
know here
no that's not true um
we're running it for four we expect this
to give 107.
wow these numbers are getting huge
that's the number of machines we're
currently running so we have to do that
many things
each step
it looks like it's kind of decreasing
though more and more machines are
halting
you know machine learning is this new
scam like you know oh i'm going to learn
i'm going to write an mnist classifier
and then i'm going to get hired as a
machine learning engineer no you're not
it's only it's it's a weird thing about
machine learning that people think this
too
like oh i'm gonna write uh like i'm
gonna follow
nobody would say i'm gonna write the
react demo app
and then i'm gonna be hired as a react
engineer nobody would say that
but yet people think this for machine
learning it's weird
rob enhancing quality you don't want
fancy machine learning you just want
linear regression and uh
cleaned up uh cleanup data
um i mean it's running it's not like at
least
this number uh here represents
the total number of uh machines in the
priority kit
and we could maybe make it faster
overall compute that cardinality every
time
how bad is that big loopies
uh
yeah we could just track that somewhere
it's making bajillions of copies over
and over and over again i guess also the
machines are getting
bigger um all right
is slido nice
um yeah that's that's that's today's
programming
tomorrow we shall finish
zany zoo imp maybe i'll do some off
stream too
um we'll see
all right let's see what we got
why don't i consider mods for the stream
because you guys ask
trash questions explain busy beaver 5
state to newcomers
go back to yesterday's video and watch
the beginning of it where i explain it
i'm not even you know
no no
it's good how much time do i spend daily
working on projects
29 hours bitches that's right this is 29
up folks there stupid question
do i like fish wow this was this was my
submitted question actually yes i had
fish for dinner last night
uh
you know i'm thinking now like what do i
expect these questions to be
this it's my fault it's my fault for not
providing any more structure in the
format
but i'm not good at providing structure
and format that's not the kind of person
i am
again like low conscientiousness
um i don't want latest questions i'm
about to go away
there we go uh
do you watch any of the streams tabs or
spaces
who in chat knows why that's a dumb
question
all right guys i just i want you to
think about what the structure
of of of oh actually yo guys you ever
seen the movie limitless man
you see that movie i should have checked
into my own private wikipedia because
this wikipedia sucks
you heard it nzt48 man oh see nzt48
it's it's real it's real and the way
that i stay motivated is i take it
and if tonight uh you come and meet me
uh you know on the corner of beverly and
wilshire
i'll hook you up with my guy
uh it's hot in new york and my air
conditioner is loud
um ambitious problems no one is focusing
on
see this is
it's not necessary i see that okay so
that's not necessarily a bad question
but that's a question that every single
vc
is asking all right oh man we gotta find
oh we got some new kid man yo i got this
guy bobby
out in a garage in south dakota man
yo yo he's working on giving
wombats the ability to type
wombat typing man like wombat typing
spreads through
spreads through the uh vc circles right
it's not about ambitious problems it's
about boring problems
no one's focusing on boring shit
um you know
but yeah that was so wrong
the joke about wombats and typing is one
that's done your dollar
type no
can you reveal anything that few people
know about comedy ai or you guys want to
know the
you guys want to know the the deep
secrets
uh
my eye has two bathrooms one of them has
a urinal
and there's something in there that kind
of looks like a shower but it's not a
shower
spell you with three letters
uh
why don't you consider mods for the
stream it won't be perfect but it might
help so i made a few people mods
um the problem is who will moderate the
moderators
right who will add new moderators
moderators come and go
uh you know i'm a slacker i don't have a
schedule right
so oh yeah let's put a real schedule
together let's put
effort into this man have you considered
a production
manager you know you could really take
your stream to the next level
oh my gosh
i didn't do any of that man honestly
i want a group of like a bunch of people
where we can all chill
and we can like read the paper
and then we can work on busy beaver 5.
like why am i going to stream this for
you again tomorrow
aside from a few people who caught a
bunch of syntax errors in my programming
it seems like people didn't read the
thing
right i gave you all homework and nobody
did it at least from what i could tell
so i'm actually gonna stream for you
tomorrow i'll work on this stuff myself
you know
and we tried to chill
yeah i don't know y'all got excuses i
don't care okay
don't really believe that girl was
stupid about gollum
go is for people too dumb to program in
c plus plus like me
so many mistakes i mean i should have
written a go i would have made way less
mistakes
um
oh they answered that uh
is it better to be an introvert or an
extrovert
oh what's this mean
what's that word mean yeah we're trying
to optimize for
you know i can't even rationally can't
answer that question i can't answer that
question
um
how's comm ai doing i can read
i probably made a post on linkedin i'm
going to post on linkedin
uh
naively it can't be done um the reason
you can't read faster
is not because you can't see enough
words because you're in a processing
loop can't
process fast enough if you want to
bootstrap that it's going to be some
crazy
complex thing that said
even though i don't get more bandwidth
than using a keyboard and a mouse
moving my fingers is so much effort
neuralink would be sick
i don't know anything about society
you know what's not a good way asking
people what's a good way
right maybe this is why you know what
google is the search engine you all
deserve
you know you all deserve google this is
the kind of
all right you know to be fair i can say
that google
made people talk stupid like this right
but i don't know i don't know i don't
know which way
i don't know which way it went right oh
let's let's google this oh yeah yeah
what is a good way
you know what you deserve news articles
and listicles for this yeah there we go
three ways to internalize what you study
cora what's the best way of
internalizing knowledge
the nine steps that will help you learn
anything ten definitions of learning
google's a search engine you all deserve
man
that's why is 30 a month it's like
subscribing but it costs more money
all right we'll get
you gotta watch watch the beginning of
the previous video for that
uh am i optimistic or pessimistic about
agi the singularity
well look man you wake up tomorrow when
you find out you don't have free will do
you do anything differently
that answers the question um
i don't know man coffee shops
i like coffee shops i don't like that
they're not indoors anymore i like
coffee shops
be right i like this question this is
the first
this is the first good question
i mean it's totally off topic but it's
legitimately a good question right
of the first question here
is is is total trash it's total trash
and this is a good question how smart
can you make a dog right
so so let's answer that um
well all right so first let's go to uh
let's go on my own private wikipedia to
uh neuron number
animals i have a feeling that this
search isn't gonna work oh beautiful
ha ha private private thingy um
okay so a dog has
two billion neurons and humans have
about a hundred a hundred billion
um a hundred billion i think when you go
by synapses it's closer but let's just
say that a
dog is uh is like 40 times
stupider than a human right um
now let's ask a a
somewhat upsetting question which is how
human how many humans are dumber
what what iq makes you dumber than a
gorilla right
um so
if we say that maybe an iq of 40
puts you on par with a gorilla it let's
say for every
let's say for every happening of the
neurons
um you end up with a
say iq yeah every happening of the
neurons
gets you a happening of iq
i mean iq is normally distributed so i'm
not sure if that
exactly is what i'm trying to say maybe
we can just go by number of standard
of standard deviations right
um i mean what i'm trying to do is i'm
trying to map like the standard
deviations of of of a human uh
and i don't know maybe this is a dumb
way of thinking about it
um
it's an interesting project it's an
interesting project you could actually
do it
and then like yeah what does a dog iq
test look like
i mean it's weird to know we shouldn't
we shouldn't go we shouldn't go by iq we
shouldn't really think about it like
that
we do know that from a raw cognitive
perspective
humans have about 40x the horsepower of
a dog
so let's just say that like everything a
human
average human can do things 40 times
faster than the average dog
um like like if you're
breeding the dogs how many st there's
some normal distribution of dog
intelligence right
and some number how many standard
deviations can you get
with breeding that the gwen thing talks
a lot about this
um using different techniques uh
we should try these things and dogs
though
what's a fun project a student to learn
go make smart dogs like that guy
um yeah so i think i think before we can
really answer the question how smart do
you think i can make a dog
we're gonna need some kind of like dog
iq test and to understand
what the mean dog and what the standard
deviation of dogs is
and then to answer that question i would
say that you could probably through
clever breeding
get dogs that are let's say
four standard deviations five standard
deviations above the mean
uh and that would correspond to humans
with an iq of well 15 times
uh 5 is 75 so like 175
iq humans right
obviously you can get a dog that yeah
yeah
uh neurons in the neocortex is probably
better but
bro
i don't know
um i saw i saw
oh i saw an upsetting on hacker news
like this country totally bumbled the
covid crisis if only they
cared more about people's lives right
it's like this please i'm desperate
okay
so
you got a sharp click what did i think
of nim
it's all right we're doing all day in
new york going on dates um
i feel like shkreli in the live streams
now you know sitting in the new york
apartment
this looks like skrelli's apartment
uh why are the questions here so bad i
mean for all the reasons that we talk
about
um well the local is it this i mean this
isn't it's off topic it's not a
really bad question i don't know we use
ekfs
could you do better with uh
with something that understands the
noise models better
i mean common filters are making uh
gaussian assumptions of
the noise they also assume that it's
uncorrelated through time neither which
are true
um but they seem to work well
i don't know
seven feet
i don't know what that is
lower than harvard
all right that was slido that's what we
tried today
i actually think that um
the subs q a from yesterday was better
uh
okay you know what here's what i'm doing
for tomorrow's stream
um if i'm not lazy which
probably won't happen but if it does
happen
uh we're gonna have a test
uh i'll try to throw together a ten
question test to see
did you read the paper um if you read
the paper
uh you're welcome into the stream uh if
you didn't read the paper you're not
welcome into the stream
and we'll have to see how we did it uh
we'll have to see how
but yeah well this is i mean this is
this is okay we can fun we can play with
we can play with these new these new
political systems before we have to
build something as expensive and intense
as the university right now
tomorrow stream for the elite
uh anyone who can pass a 10 question
reading comprehension test on the paper
i'll drop the test all at once
uh i'll have you
put in your twitch username before you
take the test
and i will trust that anyone who's smart
enough to pass it
won't share the answers with everybody
or put it this way the minute i see that
answers are shared
i can cut it off there so be somewhat
fast as well
um yeah read the paper read the paper
boys read the paper all right um
we'll see what if no one passes the test
that's that'd be the real sad thing
right
how many people we got you have 864
viewers right
uh what happened to the search engine uh
honestly
after today i realized that google was
the search engine you all deserved
after reading those questions today i
now no longer believe google is evil
i now believe that the average google
user is just just an idiot
um you guys want listicles you guys want
to search for things just
how can i be
good programmer
oh yes oh and you would love to click on
10 effective ways to be a good
programmer or
eight ways to become a better coder or
how to become a good programmer in
college
wow that applies to me i'm in college
oh how to be a great programmer and how
to become a
very good programmer with a bs how to
become the best programmer in the world
a beginner's guide on how to improve
your programming skills
be a better programmer in six easy steps
google is the search engine you guys
deserve
oh i don't know yesterday we tried
having faith in humanity
uh today we tried not having faith in
humanity and tomorrow we're going to try
building a wall we're going to build a
wall the wall is going to be made of 10
questions
um read the fucking paper
i don't know how i'll set it up
will there be a hidden stream i don't
know
be multiple choice no it'll be graded by
my army of tas
uh make the corona pay for it yeah
should have incorporated a whole bunch
of uh quick scam companies and gotten
those ppp monies
how many people can we yeah i will be
100 to enter no
no i think it'll actually be 50 i think
if you've managed to get
that won't be 50. but it won't be i
think it'll be 80
make it 80 or something
um
this is visual basic for beginners oh
i'm reading the chat on my phone we can
bring it up here
um
yeah but yeah we'll see we'll see we'll
see if i if i do a stream tomorrow it's
definitely not going to be for everybody
um
and you're putting so much work into the
stream
don't say i put in any work until i put
in any work i'm just shit talking about
hypothetical work i might do tomorrow
right
if i actually do any of this i'll be
impressed with myself i'll
pat myself on the back it's probably
because i read
eight ways to be more productive with
the limited time we have on earth
um
the questions will be relatively easy
stuff too about like you study the busy
beaver problem in general
right understand what a turing machine
is in general
uh now the date tomorrow night all day
tonight all right plans tonight
um
is a quad top player what does that mean
uh how do i end up talking to the
homeless one i went for a walk
uh and she started talking and i
responded
uh it was nice it was a rainy night it's
a nice
what time is tomorrow's stream
oh oh you know what i'm going to put a
entry in my calendar
um
all right thank you all for watching
i appreciate those who subscribe i also
appreciate those who
make good comments everybody else
i don't appreciate you
good everybody